Guide to the Brooklyn schools collection 1985.054
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn schools collection
1828-2015
Center for Brooklyn History
Brooklyn Teachers Association
New York City Technical College
St. John's University (New York, N.Y.)
Shore Road Academy (New York, N.Y.)
Colby Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
South Brooklyn Female Seminary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Caldwell Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
P.S. 35 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Columbian Institute and Kindergarten (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Union Missionary Training Institute
College Grammar School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
De Severinus Academy of Fine and Applied Art (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
East Midwood Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Grammar School 35 (New York, N.Y.)
Alexander Hamilton Vocational High School (New York. N.Y.)
St. Francis College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Prospect Hill School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Normal School for Physical Training
Prospect Heights School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Misses Peck School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Music School
Nassau Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Music School Settlement (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Catherine's Hall (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Post-Graduate Medical School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Joseph's College for Women (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Preparatory School
Trinity School (New York, N.Y.)
St. Michael's Diocesan High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Bryant & Stratton Business College
Brooklyn College
Roosa School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Ann's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Miss Dudley's Seminary for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Greenleaf Female Institute
School District 15 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Miss Hall's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Harrison and Ranney's English and French Boarding and Day School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Miss Whitcomb's French, English, and German Day School for Young Ladies and Children
Heffley School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Miss Round's School for Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Harvey's Select School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Miss Katherine L. Maltby's Home and School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Hebrew Educational Society of Brooklyn
Kingsborough Community College
Misses Crawford's School for Boys and Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Long Island Business College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Prospect Park Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Lafayette Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Latin School for Boys
Lafayette High School (New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Eastern District High School
Lockwood's New Academy
Long Island University
Brooklyn Friends School
Master School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Froebel Academy
Van Doren's Institute for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Groschel Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Walt Whitman School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies
Brooklyn College of Pharmacy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Law School
Brooklyn Juvenile High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Heights Seminary
Berkeley Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Bedford Heights Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brevoort School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Community-Woodward School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Auburn Academy and Educational Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Academy of the Visitation (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Abraham Lincoln High School (New York, N.Y.)
Bay Ridge High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Evening High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn High school of Women's Garment Trades
Brooklyn Technical High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Catherine McAuley Commercial High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Cathedral College of the Immaculate Conception
C.F. Young School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
1985.054
18.7 Linear Feet in seven manuscript boxes, one flat box, one oversize folder, and two shelves of loose volumes
The Brooklyn schools collection consists of materials relating to over seventy Brooklyn schools, both public and private, ranging from nursery schools to post-graduate institutions. Schools that are more robustly represented in the collection are Erasmus Hall High School, Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Brooklyn College, Brooklyn Technical High School, and St. John's University.
Historical note
In colonial New York, young people primarily received education through private schoolmasters and tutors, and free schooling was available to poor families through the Dutch Reformed and Catholic churches. Following the establishment of a state government, the Regents of the University of the State of New York granted charters for secondary schools in the state; the first charter, in 1768, was for Erasmus Hall Academy, located in the present-day Brooklyn neighborhood of Flatbush. Individual school districts in Kings County were created based on village, town, or neighborhood boundaries, with each district receiving funding from local taxes, state contributions, and student tuition. This system continued into the mid-19th century, when Brooklyn created a municipal board of education in 1843 to oversee all schools in the city.
In colonial New York, young people primarily received education through private schoolmasters and tutors, and free schooling was available to poor families through the Dutch Reformed and Catholic churches. Following the establishment of a state government, the Regents of the University of the State of New York granted charters for secondary schools in the state; the first charter, in 1768, was for Erasmus Hall Academy, located in the present-day Brooklyn neighborhood of Flatbush. Individual school districts in Kings County were created based on village, town, or neighborhood boundaries, with each district receiving funding from local taxes, state contributions, and student tuition. This system continued into the mid-19th century, when Brooklyn created a municipal board of education in 1843 to oversee all schools in the city.
While the number of schools in Brooklyn grew, very few educational opportunities existed beyond the primary grades for the children of poor or working class parents. Secondary schools such as Erasmus Hall and the Brooklyn Female Academy (opened in 1846, and now known as the Packer Collegiate Institute) were private, and therefore only affordable for middle class and wealthy families. The Central Grammar School, founded in 1878, was the first public school in Brooklyn to offer secondary level classes. Out of Central Grammar School, Boys' High School and Girls' High School, the first public high schools in Brooklyn, were formed to meet the demand and need for free public education beyond elementary school. Higher education also became available in Brooklyn around this time, as the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute (now known as Polytechnic Institute of New York University) conferred its first baccalaureate degrees in 1871, and St. Francis Academy evolved from a monastery and preparatory school to St. Francis College in 1885.
Sources
Lopate, Carol. Education and Culture in Brooklyn: A History of Ten Institutions. Brooklyn, N.Y.: Brooklyn Education and Cultural Alliance, 1979.
Ment, David. "Public schools." In Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, 955-961. New Haven: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was formally accessioned in 1985. Sources and dates of acquisition for the bulk of materials is unknown. PS 139 Class of 1917 photograph gift of Lynn Washbourne Williams, 2011. Erasmus Hall High School class of 1932 photograph is the gift of Roy Nydorf, Ethan Nydorf, and Amy Moore, in loving memory of their father Seymour Nydorf, 2017. Girl's High School yearbook (1947) is the gift of Linda Chelmow, 2017.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society holds several related collections, including records from schools such as Boys' High School, Girls' High School, Packer Collegiate Institute, Pratt Institute, and the Brooklyn Collegiate and Polytechnic Institute.
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn schools collection consists of materials relating to over seventy Brooklyn schools, both public and private, ranging from nursery schools to post-graduate institutions. Schools that are more robustly represented in the collection are Erasmus Hall High School, Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Brooklyn College, Brooklyn Technical High School, and St. John's University. Materials in the collection include school catalogues and circulars; student yearbooks; anniversary publications and histories; brochures; programs; newsletters; commencement programs; addresses; certificates of incorporation and articles of association; annual reports; photographs; and alumni directories and publications.
The collection also includes one volume titled Souvenir of Our Public Schools, Brooklyn N.Y., which includes school staff listings, portraits of principals, and photographs of public school buildings in Brooklyn, dating from 1892.
Alumnae and alumni; Alumni directories; Annual reports; Brochures; College students |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls |x Education (Primary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls |x Education (Secondary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls' schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York; Histories; Music education; Newsletters; Programs (documents); Publications; School yearbooks; Student publications; Student life and customs |z New York (State) |z New York; Students |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Teachers Association; New York City Technical College; St. John's University (New York, N.Y.); Union Missionary Training Institute; Caldwell Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Shore Road Academy (New York, N.Y.); Bryant & Stratton Business College; Columbian Institute and Kindergarten (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 35 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Colby Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Alexander Hamilton Vocational High School (New York. N.Y.); Grammar School 35 (New York, N.Y.); Commercial High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); De Severinus Academy of Fine and Applied Art (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Latin School for Boys; East Midwood Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Nassau Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Normal School for Physical Training; Trinity School (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Hill School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Joseph's College for Women (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Music School; St. Francis College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Misses Peck School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Music School Settlement (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Roosa School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Post-Graduate Medical School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Catherine's Hall (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Preparatory School; Brooklyn College; South Brooklyn Female Seminary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Michael's Diocesan High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); College Grammar School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Harrison and Ranney's English and French Boarding and Day School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Hall's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Heffley School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Ann's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Whitcomb's French, English, and German Day School for Young Ladies and Children; Harvey's Select School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); School District 15 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Round's School for Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hebrew Educational Society of Brooklyn; Miss Katherine L. Maltby's Home and School for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kingsborough Community College; Long Island Business College (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Misses Crawford's School for Boys and Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lafayette Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lafayette High School (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lockwood's New Academy; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Eastern District High School; Master School of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Friends School; Long Island University; Van Doren's Institute for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Froebel Academy; Walt Whitman School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Groschel Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Miss Dudley's Seminary for Young Ladies (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Greenleaf Female Institute; Brooklyn Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies; Brooklyn College of Pharmacy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Law School; Brooklyn Juvenile High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights Seminary; Berkeley Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bedford Heights Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brevoort School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Conservatory of Music (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Community-Woodward School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Auburn Academy and Educational Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Academy of the Visitation (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Abraham Lincoln High School (New York, N.Y.); Bay Ridge High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Evening High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn High school of Women's Garment Trades; Brooklyn Technical High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Catherine McAuley Commercial High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Cathedral College of the Immaculate Conception; C.F. Young School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Abraham Lincoln High School, 1997-2001 (Box 5)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains two programs from the Abraham Lincoln High School Florida Alumni Chapter Reunions dated 1997 and 2001. Donated by Mindy Turkenitz.
- Academy of the Visitation, 1881-1892 (Box 1)
- Adelphi College, 1923-1924 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains two copies of the yearbook the Oracle from 1923 and 1924, donated by Rose Marie Sinnott.
- Adelphi College, circa 1930s (Box 1)
  Contains a circa 1930s recital program.
- Arlington School No. 108, 1928 (Box 1)
- Auburn Academy, 1963 (Box 1)
- Bay Ridge High School, 1927 (Box 5)
  Contains a copies of Maroon & White, 1923 - 1927. The 1927 copy was donated by Regina O'Grady-LeShane.
- Bay Ridge High School, 1949 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook the Maroon & White from 1949.
- Bedford Heights Institute, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
- Bedford Institute, 1882-1935 (Box 1)
- Berkeley Institute, 1890-1965 (Box 1)
- Brevoort School, 1898-1899 (Box 1)
- Brooklyn College, 1931-circa 2000s (Box 2)
  Contains a pamphlet entitled "Honor Students, School of General Studies," dated 1975. Donated by Mindy Berlin Turkenitz.
- Brooklyn College, 1946-2010 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the yearbook the Broeklundian from 1946 and 1962. Also contains a copy of Brooklyn College Alumni Today from 2010, donated by Doris Berlin and Mindy Berlin Turkenitz.
- Brooklyn College of Pharmacy, 1894-1895 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Collegiate Institute for Young Ladies, 1831 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Community-Woodward School, 1955-1957 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Conservatory of Music, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Evening High School, 1933 (Box 5)
  Contains a copy of the Pegasus from June 1933, donated by Richard Cantu.
- Brooklyn Friends School, 1806-1967 (Box 6)
- Brooklyn Heights Seminary (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Heights Seminary, 1851-1919 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn High School, 1849 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn High School of Women's Garment Trades, 1939 (Box 5)
  Contains a program from the Brooklyn High School of Women's Garment Trades Commencement dated June 27, 1939. Donated by Richard McHugh.
- Brooklyn Juvenile High School, 1855-1874 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Latin School, 1899-1900 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Law School, 1903-1971 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Music School, 1957-1974 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Music School Settlement, 1910-1919 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Normal School for Physical Training, 1886 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Post-Graduate Medical School, 1907-1909 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Preparatory School, 1887-1956 (Box 3)
- Brooklyn Preparatory School, 1931 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook The Blue Book from 1931.
- Brooklyn Teachers Association, 1910-1926 (Box 3, Box 4)
- Brooklyn Technical High School, 1937-2006 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the yearbook the Blueprint from 1937, 1961 to 1965, 1968, 1970 to 1971, 1973, 1977 to 1982, 1984 to 1994, 1996 to 2006. Also contains programs from the 2000 Hall of Fame Dinner and the 2012 90th Anniversary Gala as well as copy of the 2001 Alumni Association report donated by Liz Sciabarra. The 1937 copy of the Blueprint was transferred from the Bronx County Historical Society's archival collections.
- Bryant and Stratton Business College, 1885-1887 (Box 4)
- Caldwell Institute (Box 4)
- Catherine McAuley Commercial High School, 1964 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook the Mercian from 1964. Donated to the Long Island Historical Society by the St. Augustine's Diocesan High School.
- Cathedral College, 1964 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook from 1964.
- The C.F. Young School, circa 1940s (Box 5)
- Club Kindergarten School, 1926 (Box 5)
  Contains a class photograph dated 1926. Donated by Elaine Harmon.
- Colby Academy (Box 4)
- College Grammar School, 1868-1886 (Box 4)
- Columbian Institute, 1876-1877 (Box 4)
- Commercial High School (Alexander Hamilton High School), 1881-1892 (Box 4)
- De Severinus Avademy of Fine and Applied Arts, 1930 (Box 4)
- East Midwood Academy, 1958 (Box 4)
- Eastern District High School, 1938 (Box 4)
- Erasmus Hall High School, 1898-1911 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains two copies of yearbook The Flying Dutchman from 1901 and 1911. Also contains three copies of The Erasmian from 1898 to 1900.
- Erasmus Hall High School, 1932 (Flat file folder 1985.054)
- Erasmus Hall High School, 1956 (Box 5)
- The Flatbush School, 1922-1924 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains three copies of the yearbook The Annual of the Flatbush School from 1922 to 1924, donated by Sharan Lee Leslie Eastwood.
- Franklin K. Lane High School, 1949 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook Senior Echoes from 1949.
- Froebel Academy, 1889-1890 (Box 6)
- Girls' High School, 1947 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook Blue and Gold from 1947. Donated by Linda Chelmow.
- Grammar School No. 12, 1901 (Box 8)
  Contains Mettie M. Harsen's diploma from the class of 1901.
- Grammar School No. 35, 1892-1896 (Box 6)
- Granberry Piano School, 1924 (Box 5)
- Greenleaf Female Institute, 1859-1861 (Box 6)
- Groschel Conservatory of Music, 1892-1893 (Box 6)
- Harrison and Ranney's English and French Boarding and Day School for Young Ladies, 1867 (Box 6)
- Harvey's Select School, 1846 (Box 6)
- Heffley School, 1936 (Box 6)
- Hebrew Educational Society of Brooklyn, 1961 (Box 6)
- James Madison High School, 1930 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook The Log from 1930.
- Kingsborough Community College, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
- Lockwood's New Academy, 1871-1872 (Box 6)
- Lafayette High School, 1959 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook The Legend from 1959.
- Lafayette High School, 1959 (Box 6)
- Lafayette Institute, 1866-1871 (Box 6)
- Long Island Business College, 1898 (Box 6)
- Long Island University, 1873-1999 (Box 6)
- Long Island University, 1970 (Box 8)
  Contains a copy of the newspaper Seawanhaka (special supplement) 1970 - will go in oversize box
- Manual Training High School, 1905-1912 (Box 6)
  Contains copy of Odd Times, 1905, and two copies of the Manualite yearbook, 1911 and 1912.
- Master School of Music, 1905-1912 (Box 6)
- Medgar Evers College, 1972-1984 (Box 5)
- Messrs. Van Doren's Institute for Young Ladies, 1828 (Box 6)
- Midwood High School, 1950 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook The Epilog from 1950.
- Mills College of Education, 1956-1964 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the yearbook The Link from 1956 to 1958, 1960 to 1961, 1964.
- Miss Dudley's Seminary for Young Ladies, 1867-1868 (Box 6)
- Miss Hall's School (Box 6)
- Miss Katherine L. Maltby's Home and School for Young Ladies, 1890-1898 (Box 6)
- Miss Round's School for Girls, 1891-1907 (Box 7)
- Miss Whitcomb's French, English, and German Day School for Young Ladies and Children, 1887-1888 (Box 7)
- Mrs. Crawford's School for Boys and Girls, 1895-1899 (Box 7)
- Mrs. Peck's School of Music, 1898-1899 (Box 7)
- Nassau Institute, 1886-1887 (Box 7)
- New York City Community College, 1965 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook The Statement from 1965.
- New York City Technical College, 1984-1986 (Box 7)
- Polytechinal Institute of Brooklyn, 1934-1938 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the yearbook the Polywog from 1934, 1937 to 1938. The 1934 copy was donated by Jeanne Torre.
- Pratt Institute, 1942 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook Prattonia from 1942. Donated by Ronald Eber.
- Prospect Hill School, 1903-1904 (Box 7)
- Propect Heights School (Box 7)
- Prospect Park Institute, 1888-1889 (Box 7)
- PS 1, 1927 (Box 5)
  Contains a contact sheet of student photographs dated 1927. Donated by Elaine Harmon.
- PS 10, 1941 (Box 5)
- PS 35, 1922-1925 (Box 7)
- PS 44, 1919 (Box 8)
  Contains a class photograph from 1919. Donated by John Manbeck.
- PS 46, 1927 (Box 5)
  Contains a photograph of the Grade 2B class, dated 1927. Donated by Elaine Harmon.
- PS 130, 1922 (Box 8)
  Contains a class photograph from 1922, dontated by Judy Lowin.
- PS 134, 1956 (Box 5)
  Contains a photograph of Class 6-3 dated April 1956. Dontaed by Catherine Flynn.
- PS 143, 1945 (Box 8)
- PS 145, 1938-1945 (Box 8)
  Contains two oversized class photographs from 1938 and one from 1945.
- PS 203, 1936 (Box 5)
  Contains the diploma of Mary Gurrera dated June 26, 1936. Donated by Richard McHugh.
- Roosa School of Music, 1957-1974 (Box 7, Box 5)
  Contains a bound collection of programs from the Roosa School of Music dated 1963 to 1974.
- School District 15 (Box 7)
- Samuel J. Tilden High School, 1969 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains a copy of the yearbook the Classic from 1969.
- St. Ann's School, 1967-1986 (Box 7)
  Contains a copy of Saint Ann's School: An Unofficial History, 1965-2015.
- St. Augustine's Diocesan High School, 1938-1968 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the yearbook the Lance from 1938, 1942, 1953 to 1954, 1956 to 1968.
- St. Catherine's Hall, 1900 (Box 7)
- St. Francis College, 1957-1996 (Box 7)
- St. John's College, circa 1908 (Box 5)
- St. John's University, 1931-1968 (Volume Library gallery shelf)
  Contains copies of the following yearbooks:
  The Closing Entry, the yearbook of the School of Accounting, Commerce, and Finance, from 1931 to 1941, 1943, 1949 to 1961, The Indian from 1951 and 1952, The Liber, the yearbook of the Schools of Law and Arts and Sciences, from 1932, Res Genstae, the yearbook from the School of Law, from 1941, 1953, 1958, 1961 Tomahawk from 1968, The Vincentian from 1948 and 1957.
  These yearbooks were donated to the Long Island Historical Society by Edwin B. Hewes, Mary Sparacio, and Marilyn Horwin.
- St. John's University, 1945-1959 (Box 7, Box 5)
  Contains issues of the Epitome student newspaper and other material.
- St. Joseph's College for Women, 1954-1956 (Box 7)
- St. Joseph's College for Women, 1967-1968 (Volume Library gallery shelf)